Remarque, Erich Maria; Papers ger077
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Erich Maria Remarque Papers
1938-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Remarque, Erich Maria, 1898-1970
ger077
0.25 cubic ft.
The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings and magazine articles, 1938-1973, related to the career of Erich Maria Remarque, a German-born writer most famous for his 1929 work All Quiet on the Western Front.
Biographical History
Erich Maria Remarque (the pseudonym of Erich Paul Remark) was a German-born writer most famous for his 1929 work All Quiet on the Western Front (Im Westen nichts Neues), which describes the brutality of World War I from a young soldier's perspective. His literary works include both novels and plays; several of his novels were made into films. Remarque was born in Osnabrck, Germany on June 22, 1898. As a young man, he served as a soldier in World War I and was wounded several times. After the war Remarque supported himself as a librarian, businessman, teacher, editor and journalist. His works were controversial and were accused of being harmful to Germany's national pride; in 1933 they were banned by the Nazis. Claims arose stating that Remarque was the descendant of French Jews. Remarque's German citizenship was revoked in 1938. He took up residence in Porto Ronco, Switzerland and lived there until emigrating to the United States in 1939. Remarque and his wife Ilse Jutta Zambona became American citizens in 1947. After divorcing his first wife, Remarque married a former Hollywood actress, Paulette Goddard, in 1958. Remarque and Goddard returned to Switzerland and lived there until Remarque's death on September 25, 1970. Remarque is buried in Ronco cemetery in Ronco Ticino, Switzerland.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings and magazine articles, 1938-1973, related to the career of Erich Maria Remarque. Remarque's life as an emigre from Nazi Germany is documented by articles and clippings related to his emigration to California, including a large collection of clippings from the Los Angeles Times. His literary career is represented by files of reviews of each of his books and by a collection of correspondence with Denver Lindley, his editor at Doubleday Books. The majority of the records in this collection are photocopies of originals found in German repositories.
The newspaper and magazine articles regarding Erich Maria Remarque's personal life and literary career include biographical articles and interviews, including an interview with Remarque's second wife, Paulette Goddard, following her husband's death and Los Angeles Times clippings related to Remarque's emigration to and residence in California. The collection contain reviews in English and German of Erich M. Remarque's various novels, including Arch of Triumph (1946), A Time to Love and A Time to Die (1954), The Black Obelisk (1957), Heaven has No Favorites (1961), Night in Lisbon (1963-1964) and Shadows in Paradise (1972). These folders are organized chronologically by book. The correspondence with publishers, 1952-1963, is photocopied from original correspondence in Germany regarding the publication of Remarque's literary works. The majority of the letters are between Erich Maria Remarque and Denver Lindley of the Doubleday Publishing Company. They discuss various literary works including A Time to Love and a Time to Die, Heaven Has No Favorites, Black Obelisk, The Last Station and Night in Lisbon. There is also some publishing related correspondence with individuals other than Lindley.
Lastly, there are articles and clippings regarding Hans Habe (also known as Janos Bkessy), a journalist, publisher. and friend of Erich Maria Remarque. It consists primarily of reviews of Habe's various publications. The majority of these are in German.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. 1979
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Literature; German fiction-20th century; German fiction-Translations into English; German fiction-Book reviews; World War, 1914-1918-Literature and the war; Publications; Clippings; Correspondence; Remarque, Erich Maria, 1898-1970; Lindley, Ernest Kidder, 1899-1982; Habe, Hans, 1911-1977
- Interviews, Interests and Personal Life, 1941-1973 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 1)
- Los Angeles Times, 1938-1964 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 2)
- Arch of Triumph, 1946 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 3)
- A Time to Love and a Time to Die, 1954-1958 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 4)
- Black Obelisk, 1957 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 5)
- Heaven has No Favorites, 1961 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 6)
- Night in Lisbon, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 7)
- Shadows in Paradise, 1932 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence with publishers, 1952-1963 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 9)
- Hans Habe Papers, 1948-1957 (Box 1 (Erich Maria Remarque Papers), Folder 10)